So it’s, I mean, in the name of God ridiculous things were done,
Takže to je, myslím, ve jménu Boha se děly směšné věci,
ridiculous things were done!
děly se směšné věci!
So He just thought: Better not talk about God.
Takže (Budha) si prostě pomyslel: Raději o Bohu nemluvit.
The first step is Self-Realization.
Prvním krokem je Seberealizace.
He was a great Sahaja Yogi I must say.
Musím říct, že byl skvělým Sahadža jogínem.
Because He said nothing doing, don't talk about God or anything,
Protože řekl, že nic nedělejte, nemluvte o Bohu ani o ničem jiném,
first you get your Realization.
nejprve dosáhněte své realizace.
That was the first condition, establish it.
To byla první podmínka, upevnit to.
Unless and until you have established your Realization, - nothing doing.
Dokud si neupevníte svou realizaci, nic nedělejte.
So He just started His own method of propagating Buddhi
Takže prostě začal svou vlastní metodu šíření Buddhi
Buddha's knowledge or you can Buddhism you can say as they call it.
Buddhovo poznání nebo, můžete říct, buddhismus, jak se tomu říká.
Of course it became ‘ism’ later on.
Samozřejmě se z toho později stal „ismus“.
So all that He started
Takže všechno, co začal
with the idea that people should first become Buddha.
s myšlenkou, že by se lidé měli nejprve stát Buddhou.
Buddha means realized, Buddha is ‘to know’.
Buddha znamená realizovaný, Buddha znamená „vědět“.
So "Buddha" means the person who has known,
Takže „Buddha“ znamená člověk, který poznal,
means the one who is a Realized soul.
znamená ten, kdo je realizovanou duší.
So what He says, “Buddham Sharanam Gachhami”,
Takže to, co říká, „Buddham Sharanam Gachhami“,
I bow, no I surrender – ‘sharanam’ means surrender,
Skláním se, ne, odevzdávám se – „sharanam“ znamená odevzdání se,
I surrender to the Buddhas - means to all the Sahaja Yogis.
Odevzdávám se Buddhům – znamená všem Sahadža jogínům.
You are all Buddhas because you know.
Všichni jste Buddhové, protože víte.
When you know, you are the Buddha.
Když víte, jste Buddha.
When that purity comes, you see in our temperament,
Když přijde tato čistota, vidíte v našem temperamentu,
that we do everything without any desire,
že děláme všechno bez jakékoli touhy,
we have got rid of all the ego.
zbavili jsme se veškerého ega.
The Buddha is awakened within us.
Buddha se v nás probouzí.
And that’s what is the importance of Buddha,
A to je důležitost Buddhy,
that He settled down Himself
že se usadil
in a place which is the most difficult place,
na místě, které je nejtěžší,
that is on the left side of your head, you see.
to je na levé straně vaší hlavy, víte.
Sometimes I've seen it projects here up to this point, you know,
Někdy jsem to viděla vyčnívat až sem, víte,
in some people they get such a terrible pain, you know,
u některých lidí to tak strašně bolí, víte,
pulling it out from there, can't imagine.
vytáhnout to odtamtud, nepředstavitelné.
So this horrible point which is -
Takže tento hrozný bod, který je -
so funny it is, sometimes it can blow up like that, you see,
tak směšný, že někdy to může takhle explodovat, víte,
sometimes it can pierce through. It’s a horrible one
někdy to může prorazit. Je to hrozný bod,
which all of you have developed quite a lot, you see,
který jste všichni dost rozvinuli, víte,
and it takes it forms in different ways and methods.
a nabývá podoby různými způsoby a metodami.
For that we have to say, “Buddham Sharanam Gachhami”,
Proto musíme říkat „Buddham Sharanam Gachhami“,
means: We surrender ourselves to Buddha.
což znamená: Odevzdáváme se Buddhovi.
Then what does He say? The second one is very good:
Co tedy říká potom? Druhý je velmi dobrý:
‘Sangham Sharanam Gachhami’:
„Sangham Sharanam Gachhami“:
I surrender myself to collectivity, ‘sangham’.
Odevzdávám se kolektivu, „sanghamu“.
‘Sangha’ is the collectivity.
„Sangha“ je kolektiv.
I surrender myself to collectivity. Ego goes down.
Odevzdávám se kolektivu. Ego klesá.
First of all Buddha who is sitting, who is the deity,
Za prvé Buddha, který sedí, který je božstvem,
which is the enlightenment,
což je osvícení,
you say: “I surrender myself to Buddha.”
říkáte: „Odevzdávám se Buddhovi.“
Secondly you say: “I surrender myself to collectivity.”
Za druhé říkáte: „Odevzdávám se kolektivu.“
Egoistical people cannot surrender.
Egoističtí lidé se nemohou odevzdat.
So, ‘I surrender myself to collectivity’,
Takže, „odevzdávám se kolektivu“,
so we say: “Sangham Sharanam Gachhami.”
takže říkáme: „Sangham Sharanam Gachhami.“
It is to Virat we are doing.
Děláme to pro Virátu.
What is the third one, is? "BuddhamSharanam Gachhami",
Co je to třetí? „Buddham Sharanam Gachhami",
"Sangham Sharanam Gachhami", the third one -
„Sangham Sharanam Gachhami", třetí -
‘Dhammam Sharanam Gachhami’,
"Dhammam Sharanam Gachhami",
Dhammam Sharanam Gachhami. ‘Dhammam’ means
„Dhammam Sharanam Gachhami". „Dhammam" znamená
the religion - the balance.
náboženství - rovnováha.
I surrender myself to religion, which is essence of you,
Odevzdávám se náboženství, které je vaší esencí,
or you can put it the other way round,
nebo to můžete říct i naopak,
that, ‘Buddham Sharanam Gachhami, Dhammam Sharanam Gachhami,
že „Buddham Šaranam Gachhami, Dhammam Šaranam Gachhami,
Sangham Sharanam Gachhami’.
Sangham Šaranam Gachhami“.
That's all. If you have achieved it then we can talk of God.
To je vše. Pokud jste toho dosáhli, pak můžeme mluvit o Bohu.
Not before that.
Ne předtím.
So these three things are to be achieved.
Takže těchto tří věcí je třeba dosáhnout.
We would put it in a Sahaja Yoga way like this:
Sahadža jógou bychom to vyjádřili takto:
First of all: ‘Dhammam Sharanam Gachhami’,
Za prvé: „Dhammam Sharanam Gachhami“,
‘I surrender myself to my virtues’.
„Odevzdávám se svým ctnostem“.
All desires can be surrendered to a virtue.
Všechny touhy lze odevzdat ctnosti.
Is it virtuous to do like this?
Je ctnostné dělat něco takového?
You can, if you are brought up that way you’ll just not do it.
Můžeš, ale pokud jsi takhle vychován, prostě to neuděláš.
You'll have no desires to do something, that is not virtuous and righteous.
Nebudeš mít žádnou touhu dělat něco, co není ctnostné a spravedlivé.
You will just not do it.
Prostě to neuděláš.
So, ‘Dhammam Sharanam Gachhami’.
Takže, „Dhammam Sharanam Gachhami“.
Then you should say, ‘Buddham Sharanam Gachhami’, means:
Pak byste měli říct „Buddham Sharanam Gachhami“, což znamená:
I surrender myself to my enlightenment.
Odevzdávám se svému osvícení.
This is the second state, when you are ascended.
Toto je druhý stav, kdy stoupáte.
Surrender myself to enlightenment.
Odevzdávám se osvícení.
Enlightenment that I've got to my Spirit.
Osvícení, kterým jsem dosáhl svého Ducha.
Is the Spirit who is going to guide you.
Duch je ten, kdo tě povede.
No more my physical, mental, emotional nonsensical temptations.
Už žádné mé fyzické, mentální, emocionální nesmyslné pokušení.
But what? Is the Spirit?
Ale kdo? Je to Duch?
And thirdly: ‘Sangham Sharanam Gachhami’, to the collectivity,
A za třetí: „Sangham Sharanam Gachhami“, pro kolektiv,
to the whole, to the Virat.
pro celek, pro Virátu.
This is the way we have to work it out.
Takhle to musíme vypracovat.
So ultimately he reached the same point,
Takže nakonec dosáhl stejného bodu,
that let me start it from myself.
tedy pojďme začít od sebe.
It's from myself to others, not from others to myself.
Je to ode mě k ostatním, ne od ostatních ke mně.
Is like treating the tree from outside, not from the roots.
Je to jako léčit strom zvenčí, ne od kořenů.
But Sahaja Yoga treats you from the roots.
Ale Sahadža jóga vás léčí od kořenů.
First you get your Realization,all right,
Nejprve dosáhnete své realizace, v pořádku,
then you learn how to surrender yourself to your Dharma.
pak se naučíte, jak se odevzdat své Dharmě.
Then you become collectively conscious.
Pak se stanete kolektivně vědomými.
Collectivity is a temperament,
Kolektivita je temperament,
is a sense of enjoyment that you get in the collective living.
je to pocit radosti, který získáváte z kolektivního života.
Unless and until you have that you have not achieved your joy.
Dokud to nemáte, nedosáhli jste své radosti.
So Buddha has played a very great role in our lives
Buddha tedy v našich životech sehrál velmi velkou roli
and He is a very great powerful force within us.
a je to v nás velmi mocná síla.
I’m very happy that Buddha Jayanti has fallen here in England,
Jsem velmi ráda, že Buddha Jayanti připadla na Anglii,
because as we say the England is the Heart of the universe -
protože jak říkáme, Anglie je srdcem vesmíru.
it doesn't matter if I say here, is any Arab here?
Nevadí když to řeknu. Je tu nějaký Arab?
I don't want to displease any Arab people sitting here.
Nechci se nelíbit žádným Arabům, kteří zde sedí.
All right. And if it is the heart
Dobře. A pokud je to srdce,
whatever you do here will circulate in the whole universe.
cokoli zde uděláte, bude se šířit celým vesmírem.
So if you can conquer your ego here,
Takže pokud dokážete překonat své ego tady,
you can even conquer the ego of Mister Reagan and these Russians.
můžete překonat i ego pana Reagana a těchto Rusů.
You can manage that. But first start it here.
To zvládnete. Ale nejdřív to začněte tady.
It has to reverse back you see, now
Musí se to vrátit zpět, víte, teď
they have to learn from you and you don’t learn from them.
oni se od vás musí učit a vy se od nich neučíte.
When it will work out you’ll be amazed.
Když to bude pracovat, budete ohromeni.
Ego is the only problem I always face reaching their hearts.
Ego je jediný problém, se kterým se vždycky potýkám, když se snažím dosáhnout jejich srdcí.
If ego is removed everything will be all right.
Pokud se ega zbavíme, bude všechno v pořádku.
So for us the great mantra is "Buddham Sharanam Gachhami".
Takže pro nás je velkou mantrou „Buddham Sharanam Gachhami“.
These three mantras you must say everyday I think,
Myslím, že tyto tři mantry si musíte říkat každý den,
to get rid of this horrible ego.
abyste se zbavili tohohle hrozného ega.